<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bitsphyassoc.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://bitsphyassoc.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-16T11:06:26-05:00</updated><id>https://bitsphyassoc.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Physics Association, BITS Pilani - BLOG</title><subtitle>The official blog of the Physics Association of BITS Pilani</subtitle><entry><title type="html">VENUS: The Sexiest Planet of our Solar System</title><link href="https://bitsphyassoc.github.io/blog/science/space/cosmos/venus/solar%20system/planets/2021/08/02/venus-planet.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="VENUS: The Sexiest Planet of our Solar System" /><published>2021-08-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-08-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://bitsphyassoc.github.io/blog/science/space/cosmos/venus/solar%20system/planets/2021/08/02/venus-planet</id><author><name>Suyash Kumar</name></author><category term="science" /><category term="space" /><category term="cosmos" /><category term="venus" /><category term="solar system" /><category term="planets" /><summary type="html">If you have ever looked up at the night sky, you must have seen the planet. Being the third brightest object in our sky after the sun and the moon, it’s pretty hard to miss. Speaking of the moon, this planet has no natural satellite of its own. The planet got its name from the Roman goddess of love and beauty, quite apt indeed. Venus, the second closest planet to our sun in the solar system, is often referred to as Earth’s twin due to its identical shape and size. Yet, there are significant differences between the two. The most obvious one is the environment on Venus which is non-conducive for life (as far as we know it yet!). The rotational direction of Venus is opposite to all the other planets in the solar system except Uranus, which shares the common event of the sun rising in the West and setting down in the East. The length of a day on Venus is equivalent to around 117 Earth days (synodic, 243 days if you wish to count sidereal), making it the planet with the longest duration of a day. Venus is the closest a planet can get to Earth, but it doesn’t stay that way for long because of its orbit. Venus is a mere (at the cosmic scale) 40 million km away from the Earth at its closest, while the farthest it can get, on the other side of the sun, is roughly 260 million km. While the orbit of other planets is elliptical, the orbit of Venus is the closest we have to a circular one. With an eccentricity of much less than 1, it is indeed the closest in our solar system.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bitsphyassoc/blog/master/images/blog/2-venus/cover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bitsphyassoc/blog/master/images/blog/2-venus/cover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Primer to the Standard Model</title><link href="https://bitsphyassoc.github.io/blog/particle%20physics/standard%20model/elementary%20particles/universe/2021/08/02/standard-model.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Primer to the Standard Model" /><published>2021-08-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-08-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://bitsphyassoc.github.io/blog/particle%20physics/standard%20model/elementary%20particles/universe/2021/08/02/standard-model</id><author><name>Abhinav Choudhary</name></author><category term="Particle Physics" /><category term="Standard Model" /><category term="Elementary Particles" /><category term="Universe" /><summary type="html">What we already know: In our high school, we were all taught about Ernest Rutherford, J.J Thompson, and James Chadwick, who discovered the proton, electron and neutron, respectively. Ernest Rutherford was further able to predict the structure of the atom. These were significant discoveries as they were a step up from the previously existing theoretical description of atoms. Protons, electrons, and neutrons were described as fundamental particles making up everything that the universe contains.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://physicsworld.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Martina-Hestericova-3-April-Quantum-computing-for-high-energy-physics_authorized.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://physicsworld.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Martina-Hestericova-3-April-Quantum-computing-for-high-energy-physics_authorized.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Remarkable Coincidences</title><link href="https://bitsphyassoc.github.io/blog/welcome/many%20worlds/physics/evolution/2021/07/24/remarkable-coincidences.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Remarkable Coincidences" /><published>2021-07-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-07-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://bitsphyassoc.github.io/blog/welcome/many%20worlds/physics/evolution/2021/07/24/remarkable-coincidences</id><author><name>Shanmugha Balan</name></author><category term="Welcome" /><category term="Many Worlds" /><category term="Physics" /><category term="Evolution" /><summary type="html">Utter emptiness. A lacuna, an oblivion of nothingness like no other. Or so we think, for nothing is certain about this place. If we can call it a place. If we can go back to before it happened. But how do you define time here? And then it happens. A blink is too long of an interval to describe it. Before you know it, there’s everything. If you were there you wouldn’t fit. If you did fit, you wouldn’t be able to see. Assuming none of the other myriad problems are our concern. After all, we neglect air resistance and higher-order terms. Soon, you have enough room growing around you, the region clears up and stuff gets moving around you. You have space to move about and so does light, meaning you can finally see. Before you know it, all the good stuff is over. The only major artifact of this fantastic event is a tiny whine which was mistaken for pigeon droppings.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bitsphyassoc/blog/master/images/blog/1-remarkable/image5.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bitsphyassoc/blog/master/images/blog/1-remarkable/image5.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>